A Guide to the James Maury Sermons, 1743-1764
John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Library, Colonial Williamsburg Foundation
John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Library, Colonial Williamsburg
James Maury Sermons, 1743-1764.
John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Library, Colonial Williamsburg Foundation
MS 91.15
10 items.
James Maury, 1718-1769.
Administrative Information
Access
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Purchase, 1991.
Biographical/Historical Information
James Maury (1718-1769) was the son of Matthew Maury and Many Anne Fontaine. He attended William and Mary and in 1742 was appointed usher of the grammar school. He was ordained as a minister in England a year later. Maury preached in King William county and later, in Fredericksburg Parish in Louisa County, Va. In the late 1750's he ran a small boarding school and had as students, Thomas Jefferson, James Madison (later Bishop), Dabney Carr and others.
Scope and Content Information
The ten sermons (1743-1764) in this collection concern prayer, lust of the flesh, Christ, inner peace, earthly needs, youth, children, the infirmities of human nature and many other subjects. The sermons consist of the Biblical reference on which it is based, the text, and a list of when and where the sermon was preached.
Arrangement
Arranged in chronological order.
Index Terms
Persons:
Maury, James, 1718-1769.
Subjects:
Sermons, American--18th century.
Corporate Names:
Church of England--Virginia--History--18th century-- Sources.
Geographical Names:
Virginia--Religion--18th century--Sources.
Contents List
- Sermon based on Matthew 6.6. Concerns "private prayer" which can be an antidote against vain-glory and hypocrisy. Includes list of when and where the sermon was preached. 19 pages, 20 July 1743.
- Sermon based on Matthew 6.6. Concerns putting "private prayer" into practice. Includes list of when and where the sermon was preached. 15 pages, 24 July 1743.
- Sermon based on Galatians 5.16. Concerns the victory over the lust of the flesh and explains what is meant by walking in the spirit. No. 72. Includes list of when and where the sermon was preached. 24 pages plus insert, 29 September 1745.
- Sermon based on Mark 16.19. Concerns Christ's sitting at the right Hand of God. No. 88. Includes list of when and where the sermon was preached. 18 pages plus insert, 18 May 1746.
- Sermon based on Psalms 37.37. Concerns man's inner happiness or peace. No. 90. Includes list when and where the sermon was preached. 16 pages, 29 June 1746.
- Sermon based on Matthew 6.33. Concerns seeking the Kingdom of God first and food, clothing and drink will come later. No. 96. Includes list of when and where the sermon was preached. 14 pages, 21 September 1746.
- Sermon based on Ecclesiastes 12.1. Concerns remembering God in one's youth. No. 130. Includes list of when and where the sermon was preached. 18 pages, 12 February 1748/9.
- Sermon based on Ephesians 6.1-3. Concerns the duties of children. Includes list of when and where the sermon was preached. 17 pages, 2 September 1750.
- Sermon based on John 3.2. Concerns teachings of Jesus. No. 177. Includes list of when and where the sermon was preached. 20 pages, 8 February 1761.
- Sermon based on Philippians 4.6. Concerns infirmities of human nature. No. 12. Includes list of when and where the sermon was preached. 20 pages, 22 January 1764.